<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="-1291841349" Content_Hash="-763728507">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>721ead24-50ca-4885-9da1-dc972b39f6c6</Id>
    <Id_History>90e8c1e8-b40d-42e7-a7aa-ad402ce13dcf,</Id_History>
    <Library_Id>26bd1a04-beed-4a66-917d-b6ab0a7d634c</Library_Id>
    <Title>How to Test for Session Hijacking Vulnerabilities</Title>
    <Category>Session Management</Category>
    <Phase>Test</Phase>
    <Technology> Any</Technology>
    <Type>How To</Type>
    <DirectLink>How to Test for Session Hijacking Vulnerabilities</DirectLink>
    <Tag />
    <Security_Demand />
    <Author />
    <Priority />
    <Status />
    <Source>SI</Source>
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="true" DataType="Html">
    <Data><![CDATA[<h1>
    <span>Applies To</span>
  </h1>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <span>Web applications</span>&amp;nbsp;</li>
  </ul>
  <h1>
    <span>Summary</span>
  </h1>
  <p>
    <span>Many web applications use session management to track visitors’ authentication state.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>For example, e-commerce sites issue a session to a client in order to verify that the client is logged in, and to display their personal information.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>An attacker’s goal during session hijacking is to steal the victim’s session and masquerade themselves as that victim.<span>&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; </span></span>
  </p>
  <p>
    <span>By masquerading as the victim the attacker can use the vulnerable site as though they are the victim, impersonating them.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>In the case of banking sites, the attacker could read the victim’s balance and potentially make transactions on their behalf.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>In the case of webmail sites, the attacker could potentially read and write emails as if they were the victim.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Attacks due to session hijacking vulnerabilities are extremely dangerous.</span>
  </p>
  <p>
    <span>When talking about session hijacking there are two victims:</span>
  </p>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <span>The vulnerable web application that allows the attacker to steal a session using methods presented here.</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>The Internet client that gets hijacked due to their session being stolen.</span>
    </li>
  </ol>
  <p>
    <span>Although the Internet client victim is most affected, the actual vulnerability exists in the server application.<span>&amp;nbsp; </span></span>
  </p>
  <p>
    <span>The following is a summary of testing steps when searching for session hijacking vulnerabilities:</span>
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <span>Step 1</span>
      <span>:<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Understand attack scenarios.</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Step 2</span>
      <span>:<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Identify high risk components.</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Step 3</span>
      <span>:<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Test and explore.</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Step 4</span>
      <span>:<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Tune test cases.</span>&amp;nbsp;</li>
  </ul>
  <h1>
    <span>Step 1:&amp;nbsp;Understand Attack Scenarios</span>
  </h1>
  <p>
    <span>The first step in testing for session hijacking is to have a solid understanding of how the attack itself is executed.&amp;nbsp;</span>
  </p>
  <p>A prerequisite in any session hijacking attack is to identify both the vulnerable web application and select an Internet client victim.&amp;nbsp;For these attacks to work the client victim needs to be an active user of the vulnerable web application.&amp;nbsp;A good example is an online banking website with session-related vulnerabilities.&amp;nbsp;Active users of the system can be found by a variety of methods, of which phishing is the most popular.</p>
  <p>
    <span>There are three common session-hijacking scenarios:</span>
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <span>Hijacking a session via cross-site-scripting.</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Predicting a session.</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Session fixation.</span>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <h2>
    <span>Hijacking sessions using cross-site scripting (XSS)</span>
  </h2>
  <p>
    <span>The most common scenario of session hijacking is due to cross site scripting (XSS) vulnerabilities.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>These vulnerabilities are fairly common and quite easy to exploit.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>If an attacker finds an XSS vulnerability in a web application, they can construct a JavaScript payload which retrieves the values of a user’s session cookie or of in-page session variables and sends them to a server run by the attacker, where it can then be used to impersonate the victim.</span>
  </p>
  <p>
    <span>In detail:</span>
  </p>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <span>The attacker finds a cross-site scripting vulnerability in a web server that they want to attack.</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>The attacker determines how sessions are managed on the site, and creates an XSS payload which exploits this.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Typically, this will take the form of a script which retrieves a session cookie or session variable value and submits it to a web server under the control of an attacker, where it is logged.</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>The attacker prepares the payload for distribution, which includes setting up one or more servers to receive the data, and finding a way to embed the payload in a clickable URL or otherwise deliver it.</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>The attacker figures out how to use the session data to impersonate a user, which probably involves manually setting a cookie value.</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>The attacker selects one or more victims.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>If the attack is targeted, the attacker will have specific users in mind and customize their approach to target those users, but much more frequently, the attacker sends out spam to “phish” for users, attempting to get them to follow an ill-crafted link.</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>If a victim clicks on the link, the website appears to load normally, and they log in as usual.&amp;nbsp;Once they’re logged in, the exploit sends their session to the attacker’s server.</span>
    </li>
    <li>The attacker then uses the logged values in real time to begin impersonating the user.&amp;nbsp;Assuming things work as planned; they can now emulate the user and conduct whatever actions within the hijacked user’s context.</li>
  </ol>
  <h2>
    <span>Predicting a session</span>
  </h2>
  <p>
    <span>Sometimes, session hijacking can be extremely simple.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>If the server assigns session IDs in a predictable manner, an attacker can just guess other valid sessions instead of going through the trouble of stealing them.&amp;nbsp;To perform this attack, an attacker logs into a site several times in succession and records the session IDs they’re given.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>If there is a predictable relationship between them, they can hijack a session by simply logging in once and then trying sessions which should fall immediately before or after their session ID.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Some servers will use a simple incrementing number, allowing an attacker who receives a session ID of 138130 to try 138131 and 138129, for example.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>In other cases, perhaps a timestamp will be added, which may take more tries, but which can still be brute-forced fairly quickly.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Slightly more secure sites will use a randomly generated number, but mistakenly use a weak random number generator.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>If the attacker can gather enough sequential or nearly sequential IDs, they can often determine the algorithm and seed used, again allowing them to guess sessions at will.</span>
  </p>
  <h2>
    <span>Session Fixation</span>
  </h2>
  <p>
    <span>With session fixation, instead of learning an existing session ID or guessing one, an attacker provides a session ID to the victim and then takes the session back over once they’ve supplied their credentials.&amp;nbsp;</span>First, the attacker loads the site and receives a new session ID.&amp;nbsp;They embed this ID into a clickable URL in such a way that the site will recognize that ID as the current session for anyone who clicks on the URL.&amp;nbsp;Next, they send this link to the victim (this attack works better for pre-selected victims) in such a way that the victim is convinced to use the link to visit the site.&amp;nbsp;When the victim logs in, the attacker starts using the session again, and impersonates the victim at will.</p>
  <h1>
    <span>Step 2:<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Identify high risk components</span>
  </h1>
  <p>
    <span>Now that you understand the kinds of vulnerabilities you need to deal with, you can start to examine how they can affect your site.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>If you have access to the source code, find all of the session management code in the system - hopefully, it will be centralized.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Even if you don’t have access to the code, you need to make a list of all pages in the system which use sessions.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Once you understand how sessions are used in the code, you need to learn how to recognize the problems and solutions around two parts of the code that can allow session hijacking vulnerabilities to occur; session generation and session ID protection.</span>
  </p>
  <h2>
    <span>Finding Session Management Code</span>
  </h2>
  <p>
    <span>If you have access to the source code of the application t</span>his will be much easier, because most applications do all of their session management in a single place.&amp;nbsp;If there is a page template in your application, chances are good that it will handle session management.&amp;nbsp; Examine the template and determine if this is true.&amp;nbsp; Figure out how to recognize if a page is using or transmitting the session data both from the source code and purely from the client side, by locating session variables in the outputted page or by viewing cookies sent as part of the HTTP transaction with a proxy like the Burp suite.&amp;nbsp; Ensure that you know where sessions are generated, and make a list of all pages in the application which handle session data, even if they don’t use it directly.</p>
  <p>
    <span>If you don’t have access to the source code of the application,&amp;nbsp;</span>this is somewhat more difficult.&amp;nbsp;Start by looking at the source code of loaded pages and the HTTP transactions sent to load them (using a proxy like the Burp suite) to determine what your session variables look like.&amp;nbsp;This will let you determine which pages in the site use sessions.&amp;nbsp;Make a list of all the pages in the application which handle session data, even if they don’t use it directly.&amp;nbsp;</p>
  <h2>
    <span>Session Generation Problems and Solutions</span>
  </h2>
  <p>
    <span>The first issue to look at is when sessions are generated. If a site has user-customized functionality, it is common that a session will be generated immediately upon loading the site, instead of when the user logs in.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>This is easy to determine by checking for the presence of a session variable attached to pages served when a user isn’t logged in.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Even if the session isn’t actually used, one may still be created immediately if session management is handled by the same template on all pages.&amp;nbsp;If a session is created prior to login, it’s critical that the old session be invalidated and a new session created when the user logs in.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>This way, session fixation attacks will fail.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Checking this is simple - just see if the session values change during login.&amp;nbsp;</span>If a site isn’t using cookies to store their sessions and the user has multiple windows open, only the window which the user used to log into the site will get the new session.&amp;nbsp;Make sure this is true if this applies to your application, or the site may be automatically converting the old session ID to a new ID, which means session fixation attacks can still work.</p>
  <p>
    <span>Now that you’ve checked when sessions are generated, look at how their IDs are generated.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Make sure that the IDs are sufficiently large and random.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Good session identifiers are at least 64 bits long; 128 is strongly preferred.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>They should never be sequential, and, whenever possible, should be generated by cryptographically secure random number generators.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Determining the degree of randomness can be difficult without access to the application’s source code; however, there are tools available, such as Burp’s sequencer, to aid in this task.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>This tool, included in the Burp Suite, can measure the degree of randomness (entropy) of session tokens generated by a specific site and determine if they are reasonably safe.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Other tools such as OWASP’s WebScarab and IBM Rational’s AppScan have similar functionality. <span>&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</span></span>
  </p>
  <p>
    <span>The final thing to look at in the session generation process is what happens to old sessions.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Sessions should time out after some time period - thirty minutes is appropriate for most applications.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>If the user logs out, the session should also be invalidated.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>It’s fairly common for insecure sites that use session cookies to simply delete the session cookies when the user logs out, but to leave the session as valid.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>If an attacker has hijacked the session, this leaves the user with no way of stopping them.</span>&amp;nbsp;</p>
  <h2>
    <span>Session ID Protections and Problems</span>
  </h2>
  <p>
    <span>There are two ways that an attacker can learn the value of a session ID - cross-site scripting and sniffing.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>There are several layers of protection which should be applied to session IDs to prevent these problems, all of which are fairly easy to test for.</span>
  </p>
  <p>
    The most basic thing that an application can do to protect session IDs is to use SSL (HTTPS) for all pages which use sessions.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Checking if a site is using SSL is easy - just check that the URLs for the site start with 
    <i>https://</i>.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>If they do, there are a few more things to look at.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>First, make sure that the site won’t allow you to change the URL back to <i>http://</i>.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Next, make sure that all the elements in the page use SSL. Your browser will tell you if it doesn’t, if it’s configured to do so.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Then, check that a proper certificate, which is signed by a well-known CA is being used, that the certificate is current, and that sufficiently strong encryption is being used - all of the information that your browser can give you.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>The last step is slightly more time consuming; you need to ensure that all pages in the site that will see the session ID use SSL.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>It’s ok if some pages don’t use SSL, as long as you check to make sure that those pages don’t ever receive, request, or embed the session ID, as it could then be stolen by an attacker with the ability to sniff a user’s connection.
  </p>
  <p>
    <span>If SSL can’t be used on the site, which is generally only a problem when supporting mobile web browsers, and going away quickly there too, hard time-outs should be used.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Normally, a session times out at some point after the user last interacted with the site.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Sites without SSL should invalidate their sessions at a fixed time after initial login unless the user logs out first, then of course it should be invalidated immediately.</span>
  </p>
  <p>
    <span>Once you’ve looked at the basics of how the session variables are passed around, look at how it’s stored on the client.&amp;nbsp;There are two options here - either as a cookie, or as a page variable.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Cookies are the preferred method, because they are easier to protect and manage.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>The session ID should never be stored in the URL of the page, as this opens up the risk of intermediate proxies or users with access to the client’s session history stealing the user’s session.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>To check for this, look at the URLs used by the site - if they contain long alphanumeric strings which seem to act like session identifiers, the pages in question are probably using this technique.</span>
  </p>
  <p>
    <span>Another method of passing around session variables is as hidden form parameters.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>The site is designed so that all links are actually HTTP POST requests, and a hidden parameter is appended to all of them.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>You can test for this in two ways; first, look at the source code to the page and see if a hidden variable of this type seems to be present.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Second, use a proxy to look at the requests which are sent to the server and see if they include such a parameter.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>This is a poor method of storing session IDs, because if the site is vulnerable to cross-site scripting attacks, the ID can be easily extracted from a page and sent to a malicious attacker.</span>
  </p>
  <p>
    <span>The preferred way to store sessions is via cookies.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>You can determine if your application stores it sessions in cookies by having your browser prompt you when it sets cookies, by examining the contents of your cookies while using the application, or by using a proxy and watching for when cookies are set.</span>
  </p>
  <p>
    If you application is using cookies and SSL, you’re doing pretty well, but there are a few things which still need to be checked.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>First, the cookie should be set as <i>SSL-only</i>.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>This ensures that even if the user does visit the site without SSL for some reason, they will not accidentally compromise their session.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Second, the cookie should be set as <i>HTTP-only</i>.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>The <i>HTTP-only</i> flag will prevent JavaScript running on the page from accessing the cookie in most cases.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>This makes it much more difficult to steal a session via XSS.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Both of these flags can be checked by examining the response from the server which sets the cookie with a proxy.
  </p>
  <p>
    <span>Although the previous protections should mostly deal with this issue, even with all of them used properly, sessions can sometimes still be hijacked via cross-site scripting.<span>&amp;nbsp; </span>It is important to conduct a full review of all pages in an application which handle session IDs.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Similar methods, such as response splitting, can also be used to perform this attack.</span>&amp;nbsp;</p>
  <h1>
    <span>Step 3:&amp;nbsp;Test and Explore</span>
  </h1>
  <p>
    <span>Now that you’ve learned what session hijacking looks like, know how recognize both insecure and secure implementations, and understand which pages in your application are likely to be vulnerable, it’s time to start testing.</span>
  </p>
  <h2>
    <span>Ensure that a new session is created at login time</span>
    <span>
    </span>
  </h2>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <span>Start capturing network traffic using Wireshark or a similar network sniffer</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Open a web browser and log in to the application site </span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Stop the capture and record the session ID value which is inside the cookie contents (this is value A)</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Log out from the application site </span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Start a new capture</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Log in to the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Stop the capture and record the session ID value which is inside the cookie contents (this is value B)</span>
    </li>
  </ol>
  <p>
    <span>Expected result:<span>&amp;nbsp;</span></span>
    <span>value A != value B</span>&amp;nbsp;</p>
  <h2>
    <span>Ensure that existing sessions are invalidated on the server upon logout</span>
  </h2>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <span>Start capturing network traffic using Wireshark or a similar network sniffer</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Open a web browser and log in to the application site </span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Stop and analyze the capture to determine what HTTP header is used to transmit the session ID (usually this is done within the Cookie header)</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Record the value of the session ID</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Log out of the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Start Burp proxy (this tool is recommended, but you can use a similar HTTP proxy tool)</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Log in to the application site and record the new session ID</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Set up Burp proxy to replace new session ID with the old one recorded in step 4</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Refresh current page</span>
    </li>
  </ol>
  <p>
    <span>Expected result:</span>
    <span>Upon refreshing the page, the application site automatically logs out the user as it detects an old session being used.&amp;nbsp;This old session ID should have been invalidated.</span>&amp;nbsp;</p>
  <h2>
    <span>Ensure that IDs are created randomly and from a sufficiently large space</span>
  </h2>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <span>Start intercepting HTTP requests traffic using Burp Proxy </span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Open a web browser and log in to the application site </span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>From Burp Proxy,<span>&amp;nbsp; </span>select the response message from the request used for log-in and send it to the sequencer</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Use Burp Sequencer to identify the token used for the session ID in the response</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Perform various logins followed by logouts so that the application can generate different tokens (the Sequencer can automate this in most cases)</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Use Burp Sequencer to analyze the captured tokens</span>
    </li>
  </ol>
  <p>
    <span>Expected result:</span>
    <span>The results show a medium to high entropy and the reliability grade is at least reasonable.</span>&amp;nbsp;</p>
  <h2>
    <span>Ensure that sessions are expired properly</span>
  </h2>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <span>Open a web browser and log into the application site under test</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Capture the user session</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Try to determine the lifespan of the current user session to determine time to test for session expiration</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Wait a short amount of time (a few seconds should suffice) after the session should have expired and reuse the session from step 2</span>
    </li>
  </ol>
  <p>
    <span>Expected result:&amp;nbsp;</span>
    <span>Upon refreshing the page, the application site disallows access to the protected resource as it detects an old session being used.&amp;nbsp;The old session ID should have been invalidated on the server.</span>
  </p>
  <h2>
    <span>Step through all pages which handle session IDs</span>
  </h2>
  <p>
    <span>Once testing of session ID generation and expiration is complete, you need to work through the list of all the pages which handle session data that you created in step two, and make sure that all of those pages handle this data safely.</span>
  </p>
  <h2>
    <span>Ensure that session IDs are only stored in cookies on all pages</span>
  </h2>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <span>Start capturing network traffic using Wireshark or a similar network sniffer</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Log into the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Browse to private and confidential pages within the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Log out of the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Stop the capture</span>
    </li>
  </ol>
  <p>
    <span>Expected results:</span>
    <span> the session IDs are only stored in the Cookie header and do not appear in the HTTP bodies of the captured packets.</span>
  </p>
  <h2>
    <span>Ensure that session cookies are flagged HTTP-only on all pages</span>
  </h2>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <span>Start capturing network traffic using Wireshark or a similar network sniffer</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Log into the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Browse to private and confidential pages within the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Log out of the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Stop the capture</span>
    </li>
    <li>
                Inspect the contents of the <i>Set-Cookie</i> HTTP header
              </li>
  </ol>
  <p>
    
      Expected results:
    
     the contents of the Set-Cookie header must include the string <i>HttpOnly</i>.<span>&amp;nbsp; </span>For example:</p>
  <p>
    <font face="'Courier New'">Set-Cookie: USER=123; expires=Wednesday, 04-Mar-08 23:12:40 GMT; HttpOnly</font>
  </p>
  <h2>
    <span>Ensure that session cookies are flagged as SSL-only when manipulating critical data</span>
  </h2>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <span>Start capturing network traffic using Wireshark or a similar network sniffer</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Log into the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Browse to private and confidential pages within the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Log out of the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Stop the capture</span>
    </li>
    <li>
                Inspect the contents of the <i>Set-Cookie</i> HTTP header
              </li>
  </ol>
  <p>
    
      Expected results:
    
     the contents of the <i>Set-Cookie</i> header must include the string <i>secure</i> in addition to <i>HttpOnly</i>.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>For example:</p>
  <p>
    <font face="'Courier New'">Set-Cookie: USER=123; expires=Wednesday, 04-Mar-08 23:12:40 GMT; secure; HttpOnly</font>
  </p>
  <h2>
    <span>Ensure that all pages use SSL if web site manipulates critical data</span>
  </h2>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <span>Start capturing network traffic using Wireshark or a similar network sniffer</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Open a web browser and check it’s configuration to ensure it is configured so that all elements use SSL</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Log into the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Browse to private and confidential pages within the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Log out of the application site</span>
    </li>
    <li>
      <span>Stop the capture</span>
    </li>
  </ol>
  <p>
    <span>
    </span>
  </p>
  <p>
    <span>Expected results:</span>
  </p>
  <p>
    <span>a)<span>&amp;nbsp;</span></span>The URLs of the pages you just browsed to all start with 
    <i>https://</i>
     and not 
    <i>http://</i>.<br />b)&amp;nbsp;If the site switches to 
    <i>http://</i>
     then the session ID is not transmitted (you can check for this in the capture.)</p>
  <h2>
    <span>Check pages for cross-site scripting vulnerabilities</span>
  </h2>
  Do comprehensive testing of your application for cross-site scripting (XSS) vulnerabilities.<br /><ol></ol><p><span>Expected results:</span><span> your application is not vulnerable to XSS</span></p><h1><span>Step 4:<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Tune test cases</span></h1><p><span>Once you’ve covered the basics, go back and double check that you’ve got everything.</span></p><h2><span>Make sure to cover all session types</span></h2><p><span>Different platforms use different names for their sessions.<span>&amp;nbsp; </span>These are the most common names in use:</span></p><ul><li><i><span>ASPSESSIONID</span></i></li><li><i><span>JSESESSIONID</span></i></li><li><i><span>PHPSESSID</span></i></li><li><i><span>CFID</span></i></li><li><span><i>CFTOKEN</i></span></li></ul><p><span>If you’re using an in-house system, make sure you understand the identifiers it uses.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Other platforms may also use identifiers not listed here - for instance, Enterprise Java Beans (EJB) has its own way of maintaining sessions.</span></p><h1><span>Conclusions</span></h1><p><span>Session hijacking occurs when an attacker steals the session ID of a legitimate user of a web service or application.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>This is usually done with cross-site scripting attacks, although other methods exist.&amp;nbsp;Stealing a session ID gives attackers the ability to impersonate the victim client on the vulnerable site.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>For example, an attacker could browse an online banking site as if they were the victim.&amp;nbsp;This makes session hijacking extremely dangerous.</span></p><p><span>To test for session hijacking bugs you need to understand how session management works and how the various session hijacking attack scenarios work. You need to learn what session hijacking vulnerabilities look like in code, along with what the mitigations to stop them look like, and how to find the areas in your application where they may exist.<span>&amp;nbsp;</span>Finally, start testing your application by looking at the most common vulnerabilities and move on from there to more complex issues.</span></p><div><div><p /><p><span></span></p></div></div>]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>